[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to say something about if... My recollectedness, done properly, involves seeing yourself in feeling, rather than the feeling in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's the same principle as it always is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollectedness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually, when a person starts doing the, like, mindfulness of the body, it's sort of, you know, I'm attending to my body, and I'm mindful of the body, I'm bringing myself back to the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you put yourself first, your point of view first, your attentions first, and then it finds the body, because you were told you should do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, the more you do it, if you do it correctly, if you start to understand that, actually, it's not about you attending to the body, but discerning that the body is there, so that you can attend it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's that knowledge of what's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you already, in a way, start seeing as yourself within the container of the body, including your own thoughts, your own feelings, within the necessary basis of the body, not other way around, as in body exists only when you attend to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like... so...
[SPEAKER_01]: Being mindful of the body, you're kind of undermining that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're fixing the perverted order of me first, body second.
[SPEAKER_00]: But so... and by fixing the order, you're directly exactly undermining that... that... primacy that you have completely assumed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Primacy?
[SPEAKER_00]: Primacy, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm, I'm, I'm... my point of view and then this or that, depending on what I choose.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the knowledge of, of the recollectedness is the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the necessary base of the body that endures regardless of what you attempt to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's discerning that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you discern that, you see that you are within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As you cannot be outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you think outside of the body, that's within the base of the body enduring, that provides you with this experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the same comes down to the feeling as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, when you're mindful of the feeling, it's immediately... because it sort of appears, one of its characteristics is kind of distant or more remote or less perceivable, so to speak, which means kind of you're assuming it's inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inside of this body or inside...
[SPEAKER_01]: Inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inside of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've got a feeling in my head.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I am that thing that has feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you learn how to discern it as something that endures, regardless of whether you attend to it or not, you get to see that that feeling endures, and you are the one who goes left and right, up and down, in terms of your thinking or actions or choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start seeing yourself fully enclosed within the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another layer of that primacy being removed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same principle, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just taking it on a different phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, again, the same, like, mind, the mood you're in, you would be regarding it as I am here, and the mood comes and goes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I remain here, and it's just I have different moods.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mood is here, and you are second to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because you always seem to be the same to you, to yourself, you assume that that's what stays unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, doesn't matter how unchanged it stays, it's always dependent upon the present enduring mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always dependent upon present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the Buddha asked, oh, if the present feeling, if the feeling is yours, when this this man said, yeah, feeling is mine, I'm like, basically, I'm the owner of my feelings, that's, that's where myself is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, well, which feeling is it then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there are three types.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't have them all three present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, which means you have no say in their arising and enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, here you are regarding as if you are the first.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are in charge.
[SPEAKER_00]: You precede them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You rule over them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, same with the moods.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, moods come and go.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, they don't actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Moods come and go would be if you can step outside of yourself and see moods come and going.
[SPEAKER_00]: You always have a mood enduring, which means mood is always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always one mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always one feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always one body.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always one image.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always one image, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within which you are in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start seeing yourself second, it doesn't matter how much you feel like you're the one that does an unchanging phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you still discern the mood that's presently enduring and then see yourself within it, not all the way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already... you're kind of aligning things rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now the mood endures, you don't have to think about it, you can then do other things, and the mood is still there, and you don't have to keep attending to it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can just, every now and then, look back, and is that mood still there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, what mood is still there?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mood is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some mood has to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good, elated, depressed, something has to be there in a state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether the mood has changed, there's still mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and you're like, oh, you don't need to... oh, I must observe how the mood changes
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mindfulness, we're calling it recollectedness, that seems to be a really good way of naming it, because it's about, basically, it's about recognizing something that's enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then recollecting it every now and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in order, that's the thing, in order for you to, in order to recognize that it's enduring,
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to... there has to be that kind of not staring at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're staring at something... Well, if you're staring at something, you put yourself first, automatically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are, aren't you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the endurance of that thing, it's secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's dependent on your attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, that's right, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why mindfulness, I kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I use this because people can relate to it, but I don't like it because it's more associated with that attentiveness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm attending to this fully.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am mindful of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can only know the thing is enduring if you're staring at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, that's actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the opposite of recollectiveness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, when you attend, you can only attend because the thing already endures that, before you attend it, and you know it, which is why you choose to attend it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you keep prioritizing your attention of the body, the body, the body, and not the knowledge that that body is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I ask you, do you still have arms?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't... Oh, wait, wait, let me check.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will know the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you want to learn how to discern that knowledge that you already know, of what's already there, that sort of precedes, at least structurally precedes, as in it comes first, within which you can attend and choose and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you stop assuming outside of yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you stop maintaining that, the whole notion of atavāda as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: By putting the second as first, because it was meant to be first.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you are putting that which is first as second, because you put yourself first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or your point of view, or your attention, or your choice, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if there is a present feeling enduring, doesn't matter how distant, how small, how pleasant, how unpleasant it might feel, you regard that as this is the basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any movement I make in regard to it is within that basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot step outside, cannot spill over, cannot become something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something different to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even your knowledge of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the thing that occurred to me, that your knowledge of something
[SPEAKER_01]: Usually, one thinks of your knowledge of some...
[SPEAKER_01]: I know this or I understand this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something that I have.
[SPEAKER_01]: I... it's something in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you are the one which is unchanging factor there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, actually, properly understanding these phenomena is about letting them come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how they... letting them... letting them reveal themselves as what... as they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the knowledge is more in them
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, in me, the knowledge is just that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Partially.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only thing is, you need to know what to look for.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the instruction, external utterance of another needs to come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, in rare cases, somebody can figure out themselves and that's when they become either Samasambuddha or Pacheco Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But generally, people need pointers.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, yes, pointers not to like invent or create this knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pointers to discern what's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now you just know what to look for and then you get to see it, because it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in you and not your creation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the characteristics of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things we talk about in terms of how the body endures that beforehand and throughout.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you cannot, as I said, you cannot sort of disturb that order.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can pretend you did.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can believe you did.
[SPEAKER_00]: But your belief makes no difference to the factual order of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body is first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body is your container.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body is the full enclosure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And everything, even the notion of outside, is on the basis of that container of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how can you know the outside without the senses?
[SPEAKER_00]: And senses are completely embodied, which means the notion of outside, real as such, is actually fully inside of the body, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's inconceivable without it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like recollectiveness of the body in a nutshell, or just a principle of that recollectiveness, sati, in a nutshell.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's the feelings, the moods, that's the principle you want to see, that you are within it, not the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you automatically uproot the ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because usually people try to
[SPEAKER_00]: Understand the non-self by saying to themselves that this is non-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Look, it's constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it cannot be mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no thus in a direct insight.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no delay.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no, oh, this and then because of that, this is the result.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with the body first, my sense of self is not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without the body first, my sense of self is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: With ignorance, birth, aging, death, loss, whatever, craving, fighting and everything else that comes with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By putting yourself first, everything revolves around that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't decide, I'll put myself second, because you'll be doing that from the sense of self, of I.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can then discern what the Buddha said, which is the order as it is, regardless of your ignorance, your belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, even if I wish that this is first, and body second, even that wish is based on the body being first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoroughly understanding that, all these wishes, beliefs, assumptions, ignorings cannot remain, because they can only remain because you're not looking at them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're only there based on your assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness develops to the extent necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The extent necessary for being unable to assume the wrong order anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being unable to assume the wrong order means being unable to take up the ownership of your own senses, your own aggregates, your own sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, like, you can be practicing, like, regardless of the state of mind you're in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, now I feel very clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then I feel very muddled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, the body is there first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not at the expense of how you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just want to put it in the right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I couldn't feel anything if the body is not there alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I couldn't be in this mood if the body is not there alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the feeling of the mood is always within the body?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, in itself, they can serve for the same principle of mindfulness, which means, if you're mindful of your feelings, basically, you're mindful of your body automatically.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're mindful of your mind, you're mindful of your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're mindful of the images and phenomena, you're mindful of your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, phenomena are much more subtle to discern this principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you see, thoughts are in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just always like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts are in my head.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it would be hard to see thoughts as the first and now within the enduring thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense of my point of view and everything else is within the enduring thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you start doing that on the level of the body and maintain it, thoughts will have to be included, eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so really it isn't so much the body or the feeling or the mood that's the important thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is that structure, that kind of order.
[SPEAKER_01]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not, oh, with this, this will be, or with this, like, when this has arisen, then this will come to be, and because of that, I cannot have it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All that is delayed, all that is secondary, and all that's not a direct insight of the patīcampāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just seeing the ground that makes any sense of self possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning the ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, your non-discernment, your discernment, it's already... it cannot be elsewhere except within that ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mindfulness is not so much about you must, you know, focus on the body or, you know, keep staying with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more... it's just recognizing anything, really, that's enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a good starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when it's completely the opposite direction of what you're attending at.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that's enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything you can attend to, it's already secondary to your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let alone secondary to your point of view, to your choice, to your own attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, the problem is in the senses, in the point of view, in your wrong attention, ayoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you cannot possibly see that, because you're focusing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're focusing on this, focusing on that, which means that which precedes that focusing, that which focusing is a result of, is completely invisible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recollectiveness needs to start by discerning what is the basis to it all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you focus or not doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: This has to be an enduring basis, inseparable from, as the Buddha would say, inconceivable apart from.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you already know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that we are so dependent on our own choices, attentions and focusing, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: sense of control, that you even turn your dhamma meditation practice into that control.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you hope, somehow, results will kind of magically pop out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as I said, if I were to ask you, do you still have legs?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are your arms still attached to your body?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes, immediately, immediately you'll say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you already know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you genuinely don't know it, if you genuinely need to know it, you would be like, oh, what do we... You would have to then look and check and find out and gather information.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you can instantaneously answer means the knowledge is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the right light, so to speak, you're not seeing its relevance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Relevance being, ah, that knowledge that I don't need to... that I cannot attend to, actually, is there, which is the reason I can attend and choose to attend these different parts of my body and so on, for whatever reasons I might do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, belief in your meditation technique or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, I need to have the body first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's tapping into that, without needing to stare at it, look at it, make it into the object of your focus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it won't be that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't focus on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can't focus on it, but you can know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like a practical rule of thumb.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're focusing on it, it's not it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you know you're focusing, you're focused on whatever, whatever is right in front of me, I'm focused on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what else do I know while I'm focused on that?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you start developing proper mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: By discerning what you already know.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that makes it possible for me to... Yeah, what is the necessary basis for me?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm choosing to focus, I don't know, on that cup.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm focusing on it, I'm examining it, I'm looking at it, I'm thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm even thinking about its significance and use and maybe I really like the cup, maybe I dislike it, whatever
[SPEAKER_00]: All those movements of the mind, that's already all second and within.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say second, I don't mean it comes after.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just mean it doesn't...
[SPEAKER_00]: It requires or... Yeah, it's second in a structural manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a second floor is second to the first floor.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they're both simultaneously there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might be focusing on the cup for whatever reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're focusing on the cup for whatever you choose to focus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually things that, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: They determine the currently enduring feeling as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what your attention would be, on the base of how you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, while that's enduring, yeah, you check.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the body still there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is something felt still there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the mood still there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, thoughts are still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what thoughts, what focusing phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is, it's there first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's enduring, which is why I cannot focus on this, this, this, this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you also get to understand and discover the... like, your own intentions behind your focusing, your actions, your desire, your hopes, your efforts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: My personal... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...thing that I can... Because they're always... that intention is always rooted in the enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In how you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that has to be there for... throughout of your endeavors.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if that thing changes, your endeavor will stop, because motivation is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't be doing it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess it's quite possible for people to think that a feeling is not necessary, but it's actually... it's just like... Yeah, because, again, they still see themselves at first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, feeling is circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_01]: This thing that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes, I'm assailed by feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most of the time, I'm not, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when the wrong order has been so perverted and, like, almost, like, like, like, solidified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that... in that... in that wrong order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now that...
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is how it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need this, I don't need that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you need to start overriding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, all you need to ask yourself is, well, are you liable to suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you remain truly, truly indifferent to whatever feeling comes your way?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only answer, the only way you can say that yes, is if you're an arahant, which means you would have undone the order, and then you would know what I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you say, oh no, I don't need, like, feelings come and go, I'm not, I'm not affected by them.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you believe you're not affected by them, now, because nothing bothers you now, but you're still affected by the pleasure, which means you will be affected by the bother, by the loss of pleasure, by not enough pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things, as the Buddha described, as the, as the base for suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, okay, so the knowledge is there already, I'm just choosing to ignore it because it makes me feel unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: The knowledge that I am liable to feelings, which means feelings precede me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feelings are more fundamental than me and my ownership of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they come and go on their own in a sense of I depend on their coming and going, yet I have no control over it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not, oh, they come and go in order to dismiss them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people go, everything shall pass.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a good way of putting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I depend on them, but I can't control them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter if they're coming and going.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether they're coming, whether they're going, you're affected by that, by coming and going.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when people say, oh, it's impermanent, it's impermanent, it will pass, they do it just to, like, just, oh, okay, it will end.
[SPEAKER_01]: To manage it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just to manage it, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not, that cannot uproot it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're still assuming that... Well, yeah, you are liable to them, whether you believe in it or not, whether you believe else... otherwise, it's... that is the factual state of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: They come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, unless... and the same, like, with all those similes in terms of spirituality and so on, it relates to this, like, oh, you climb the tree in the pursuit of pleasures and so on, to eat mangoes and whatnot, and, you know, that tree will have to come down, either somebody will cut it or what, and if you don't come down, you will be killed by falling from great height.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, same.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are the one who goes into the domain of feelings, the body, through your ownership assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, as the Buddha said, like borrowing, borrowing jewelry, borrowing gold, and then becoming dependent on that pleasure and admiration that you get from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, deep down, you know you took it, you borrowed it, you did not create it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are not... it's, it's, it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Think that the owner could come at that moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you know that the owner will come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just choose to believe that, like, you'll deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll deal with that when that happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: And usually, if you maintain with that, in that, keep that view, it'll be too late to do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The longer you keep that view, the harder it will be to undo it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the more you kind of grow accustomed to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's like, oh, so where's the problem now?
[SPEAKER_00]: So I start focusing, I'll focus on my body and maybe, like, you know, become familiar with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already the result of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is
[SPEAKER_00]: To what happens to the body, you cannot remain emotionally indifferent.
[SPEAKER_00]: What happens to feelings, you cannot remain emotionally indifferent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Moods, you cannot remain emotionally indifferent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you are still, again, by assuming that you come first, and then second, you make yourself liable to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: By seeing it correctly, you
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, you pull yourself out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are not anymore engaging with on... and that's why you abandon the Amāra's domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't chase Amāra away.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are the one in his property.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, what is... the Buddha said, what is the property of Amāra that you take, because of which, you know, everything can ascend you, Amāra can control you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the eye, the sights, the nose, the smells, all the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he goes, okay, so it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that can be Amāra's.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not about, oh, this is not mine, this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about seeing it coming first, enduring first, being given to you for use, and then maintaining that context, maintaining that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I can ask you now, can you focus on your feet?
[SPEAKER_00]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you feel hot or cold in your feet?
[SPEAKER_00]: A bit cold.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you focus on a particular aspect of your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would it be possible for you to focus on your feet, to tell me
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever perception is down there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the body is not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you completely ignore that which you already know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then start to just like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just focus.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just look closely and closer and closer and somehow see the magical reality behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you find... if you find yourself, for example, can't help but focusing on this or focusing on that,
[SPEAKER_00]: You think, I must stop this.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to see that the body is a necessary base, enduring, while you're focusing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then your focusing becomes redundant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will focus only when there is a purpose to focus.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't focus for some projected idealistic purpose of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, the possibility of... the fact that I'm focusing on my left cold foot right now, is just one of the options that have been presented by this body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the irony of it is, the more you
[SPEAKER_00]: Prioritize focusing in order for you to discover your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The further away from the body you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you are, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your body is that knowledge that precedes the focusing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, your notion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you are so unaware of it, you have no means of discerning it, that the only way you can get a sense of body is with these body sweeping techniques and focusing of knees and shoulders and belly and top of my head and tongue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, okay, keep doing, keep moving, keep moving and then you get a sense of body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already like a secondary second.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the sense of body, that's a necessary basis for you to even begin that focusing, let alone recreate another image of the body from your focusing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... it's kind of... it's reductionist, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: I just realized as you said that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's reductionist in order to rebuild it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You... you focus on this, then you focus on that, and you focus on that, so that you can add it all together to create this nice little... And... and... what?
[SPEAKER_00]: And what remains first throughout that?
[SPEAKER_00]: The body that makes all that possible in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Factually.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for the person who does that, it's their sense of self remains first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when they rediscover their body through their cessation watching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're creating.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still, oh, I'm gonna create it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This has resulted from my effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I am the first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, it comes down to sense of control.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, it comes down to pursuit and fulfillment, which is the principle of sensuality as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you end up doing that, you're observing senses, on the basis of the senses, pursuing it, getting what you want, building what you want, seeing what you want, you're just meditating with your own centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha so many times said.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he literally, like, focusing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know how people say, oh, you can, like, like, the soldier is focused on his aim, it's mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh,
[SPEAKER_00]: Often, you hear similar kind of comparisons.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you find a certain bit where it says, yeah, yeah, it's like a cat focused on a hole where a mouse is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or an owl focused on a mouse, a cat on a fish, a crane on a fish.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't remember anymore which animal was hunting which one.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you realize, ah, so it was the hunter's focusing type.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like full-on focus.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing else exists for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm 100% focused and my aim
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said that is meditating with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because of that, you over-meditate, mis-pre.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot meditate because you don't see the background, you don't see the right context for which you need knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if your practice is practice of focusing, sensation watching or aiming or, you know, narrowing,
[SPEAKER_00]: You are like a jackal, like a cat, like an owl, like an animal trying to catch its prey.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people think that's kind of lofty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's like one-mindedness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha mocked it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha mocked it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They call them, people who meditate like that, call themselves meditators.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, here they are, shoulders and head drooping and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's all they do is meditate with their own centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, you might not be pursuing the sense object in itself, in terms of the common sense objects of pleasure, but you're still pursuing the objects of your focusing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means they're still objects of your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I guess that...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's still objects of your sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that move away from the grosser...
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of sensuality feels like, oh, this is healthy, this is good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you only move away from it, like, circumstantially.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the nature, you're still within the same framework.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how much you do that type of meditation, you're still within the domain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the danger is, of course... Well, the danger is you can't sustain that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can focus only at certain periods of time and, yeah, you can push yourself eight hours a day, do a three-month retreat in whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you develop views on top of it as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, you cannot remain indifferent.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot remain indifferent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the fact that you are drilling down in the direction of central focusing, so far away from the context that's necessary for even you beginning to do it, means the further you go, the less you'll be able to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so...
[SPEAKER_01]: Your understanding of what the body is, is... Oh, it's going to be a screen skew.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, like, yeah, exactly, far and far removed from what actually is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you could still technically know it, if you were to decide, oh, wait a minute, I already know this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you have a body?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe I develop that knowledge without needing to focus on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's going to be harder and harder to do, because each time you choose to double down on your focusing technique,
[SPEAKER_00]: Aim at a prey, or whatever goal you want, each time you end up investing yourself more, which means you're going to have more views on account of it, more significance to it, and it will be harder to undo it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same with the object of my meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: When people ask for the object to focus on, it's literally, tell me what to hunt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tell me what to stare at centrally, with the senses assumed first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yuri, come on, man.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you go?
[SPEAKER_01]: Go back.
[SPEAKER_00]: The... Tell me what to... what to khandhā.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tell me what to... what to... what to watch and observe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, not tell me what to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the object of meditation should be that which you cannot make a focusing object.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's what I was thinking, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's about understanding phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: The understanding... We're talking about body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you... do you feel anything now?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant, unpleasant, neutral?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, did you need to stop sitting, resting your arms, thinking what you're about to think, in order to find out that answer?
[SPEAKER_00]: That was already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You answered immediately.
[SPEAKER_00]: As soon as I finished a sentence, you asked me what you felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, learn how to then see what's already there, without needing to stop doing everything else and attend to it and find it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in doing that,
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm trying to say, you're sort of... it's coming... becoming familiar with something that you... you can't know by looking at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't observe your feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because that comes first, and I'm fully enclosed within it,
[SPEAKER_00]: I, I, it's like, I can't... You can't say what side of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't... You can't relate to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Relate to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't... No, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just have to allow that thing to reveal itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you, even when you forget about it, your forgetting of it is within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where you can remember it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where you don't need to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm always...
[SPEAKER_00]: I must always have it present in my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your mind, you are a result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't choose to hold this presently.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's going to be present for as long as it is present by itself, in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to say, I know this or I understand this, almost the old way would be, I am doing...
[SPEAKER_01]: I come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But really, when you can properly say, I know this or I understand this,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about stopping doing anything in relation to it and allowing...
[SPEAKER_00]: Relative stopping, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like stopping continues.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, doing continues, but it ceases to be a doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing in terms of movement, attitude towards it, that's all within.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, whether you choose to focus on it or forget about it, all of that
[SPEAKER_00]: It makes no difference to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning that doesn't stop the doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It removes the passion from the doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It removes the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't stop the doing in relation to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It stops the doings.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were dependent on the passion, on the wrong order, and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't stop all doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is maintain that right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: This container of the currently felt feeling in you is regardless of whether I weigh my arms, talk to you, talk fast, talk slow, sit down, go silent.
[SPEAKER_00]: I still feel the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Forget about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I forget about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: We start talking about something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then I remembered it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Time has passed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Passing of the time is within the duration of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling is not in time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, oh, it's the same feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't even have to think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just need to know it, whenever I remember it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at the end of the day, I remember, oh, it's still the same feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you were basically recollected throughout the day without making effort to be recollected, without thinking it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By... whenever you remember it, so to speak, you remember the correct order, which means, eh... nothing that's happening right now, eh... cannot prove that order, cannot change that order.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's seen against the right light.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and there again, I said many times, that's what Buddha said, you can't have too much of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have too much of the knowledge of what's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can have too much of investigation, you can have too little of, I just can't think about anything, but you can't have too much of knowing that the right principle of mindfulness, the body is already there, the feeling is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the body is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but not theoretically.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the feeling is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: I feel pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, within that pleasure now, all the intentions, everything you choose to do, will be within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means that type of feeling that's currently enduring for you, will be influencing everything within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That kind of precedes your choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the basis for your choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also how you stop being attached to pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you realize, oh, it's... it's not up to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, pursuing it... Can you pursue the pleasure unless it's for you?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless it's for me to be felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless you assume I'm first and that's the feeling that's my end goal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But wait, I already feel...
[SPEAKER_00]: I already feel the end goal as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I don't have it the way I want it, or similar, which means... Oh, so actually, my pursuit of pleasure is rooted in already feeling the pain of not having it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can I change the order of that pain by getting... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's second to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always second to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't be able to pursue pleasure if you don't feel anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when do you perceive pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: When you want to escape the pain and when you don't have enough of pleasure, which is painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not having enough of pleasure is painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you pursue pleasure when you feel pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, here you are believed that your pursuit and accomplishment of pleasure is somehow gonna kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Replace everything and stay with you because you created it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the only reason you were even making the effort to create that pleasure is because you were subjected to the feeling in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that pleasure you're chasing is another feeling you're going to be subjected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you get the pleasure, you can't get the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't get it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can make yourself subjected to pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Circumstantially.
[SPEAKER_00]: Make yourself subjected to pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You may find that a certain feeling arises that you were hoping for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes you pursue the same thing and, oh, it doesn't feel the same anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, oh, wow, I got so much pleasure from this, I didn't expect it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're always liable to feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for as long as you keep pursuing it in a manner of, I'm first and I'm getting this, you maintain the order that you are first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you remain completely oblivious to the fact that you are liable to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because of what you feel, or how you feel it, it's because you just keep trying to... Well, you keep maintaining that discrepancy of the assumption that I'm first and feeling you, like... Because each time you put yourself first, you imply that you're master of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Master of the body, master of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when those things don't go the way you want them, you suffer because... Not because they didn't go the way you want, but because of your mastery caused the...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no discrepancy that's felt this pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you wouldn't suffer if somebody comes and cuts down the tree and you sit back.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just wouldn't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the act of cutting the tree is not the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if someone cuts down the tree while you're trying to keep it up there and holding it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: While you're climbed up at the top.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you come down, cutting of the tree still occurs, but no emotional result in you.
[SPEAKER_00]: No suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you refuse to give up the mastery, and this is my tree, yeah, I don't care.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the time you come down, I've already cut it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can remain like indignant and hold on to what's yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it's truly yours, nobody could cut it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody could uproot it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody could destroy it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there really the fact here, the case?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just your own intoxication.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a drunk man.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I can do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can fight.
[SPEAKER_00]: A hundred people and I can win.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you slip and fall by yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you choose to refuse to give it up, despite all the evidence that you should.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, look, they're coming with the axes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Death, old age, sickness around me and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll keep that all aside.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all gonna stay for me, because basically you're in charge.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's my practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why even things like aging, death, sickness, are not suffering in themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Chopping of the tree doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It only matters if you're in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like those arahants in the suttas when the Buddha died.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they said, like, oh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, Sariputta died as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, of course, how can that which has arisen not pass?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's... like, it's inconceivable to grieve, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It requires this extreme level of intoxication to grieve over death.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a verse somewhere in the Theragata, something like, indifferent towards life, indifferent to life, indifferent to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you mean the one, I delight not in life?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I delight not in death.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wait my time, like, hiring his wage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, literally, it's like, you're out, so there's nothing felt, regardless of whether the tree stays up for longer or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to have a preference over weather,
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm subjected to feelings or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the result of you already being subjected to feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't stop having a preference, but you can start seeing the right context of that preference, which is that, oh, it's second to the already enduring feeling, which is why I prefer this over that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.